Chapter 110.
quiqu in his coffin.
Upon searching, it was found that the casks last struck into the hold were
perfectly sound, and that the leak must be further off. So, it being calm
weather, they broke out deeper and deeper, disturbing the slumbers of the
huge ground tier butts, and from that black midnight sending those gigantic
moles into the daylight above. So deep did they go and so ancient and corroded
and weedy the aspect of the lowermost punchions that you almost looked next
for some moldy cornerstone cask containing coins of Captain Noah with
copies of the posted placards vainly warning the infatuated old world from
the flood. Tears after tears too of water and bread and beef and shooks of
staves and iron bundles of hoops were hoisted out till at last the piled decks
were hard to get about and the hollow hull echoed underfoot as if you were
treading over empty catacombs and reeled and rolled in the sea like an airfraed
demig john. Topheavy was the ship as a dinnerless student with all Aristotle in
his head. Well was it that the typhoons did not visit them then.
Now at this time it was that my poor pagan companion and fast bosom
friendquake was seized with a fever which brought him nigh to his endless end.
Be it said that in this vocation of wailing sicures are unknown. Dignity and
danger go hand in hand till you get to be captain. The higher you rise the
harder you toil. So with poor Quiquake, who as harpooner must not only face all
the rage of the living whale, but as we have elsewhere seen, mount his dead back
in a rolling sea, and finally descend into the gloom of the hold, and bitterly
sweating all day in that subterranean confinement, resolutely manhandle the
clumsiest casks, and see to their stowage. To be short, among whalemen,
the harpooners are the holders, so-called. Poor Que, when the ship was
about half disembowled, you should have stooped over the hatchedway, and peered
down upon him there, where, stripped to his woolen drawers, the tattooed savage,
was crawling about amid that dampness and slime like a green spotted lizard at
the bottom of a well, and a well, or an ice house, it somehow proved to him,
poor pagan, where, strange to say, for all the heat of his sweatings, he caught
a terrible chill which lapsed into a fever. labor, and at last, after some
days suffering, laid him in his hammock, close to the very sill of the door of
death. How he wasted and wasted away in those few long, lingering days, till
there seemed but little left of him but his frame and tattooing. But as all else
in him thinned, and his cheekbones grew sharper, his eyes nevertheless seemed
growing fuller and fuller. They became of a strange softness of luster and
mildly but deeply looked out at you there from his sickness. A wondrous
testimony to that immortal health in him which could not die or be weakened. And
like circles on the water which as they grow fainter expand, so his eyes seemed
rounding and rounding like the rings of eternity. An awe that cannot be named
would steal over you as you sat by the side of this waning savage and saw as
strange things in his face as any beheld who were bystanders when Zoroaster died.
For whatever is truly wondrous and fearful in man never yet was put into
words or books. and the drawing near of death, which alike levels all, alike
impresses all with a last revelation, which only an author from the dead could
adequately tell. So that, let us say it again, no dying Caldi or Greek had
higher and holier thoughts than those whose mysterious shades you saw creeping
over the face of poor Quem,
and the rolling sea seemed gently rocking him to his final rest, and the
ocean's invisible flood tide lifted him higher and higher towards his destined heaven.
Not a man of the crew, but gave him up.
And as for Quiquake himself, what he thought of the case was forcibly shown
by a curious favor, he asked. He called one to him in the gray morning watch
when the day was just breaking and taking his hand said that while in
Nantucket he had chance to see certain little canoes of dark wood like the rich
warwood of his native isle and upon inquiry he had learned that all whalemen
who died in Nantucket were laid in those same dark canoes and that the fancy of
being so laid had much pleased him. For it was not unlike the custom of his own
race, who after imbalming a dead warrior stretched him out in his canoe, and so
left him to be floated away to the starry archipelos.
For not only do they believe that the stars are, but that far beyond all
visible horizons, their own mild, uncontented seas interflow with the blue
heavens, and so form the white breakers of the Milky Way. He added that he
shuddered at the thought of being buried in his hammock according to the usual
sea custom, tossed like something vile to the death devouring sharks. No, he
desired a canoe like those of Nantucket, all the more congenial to him, being a
whaleman, that like a whaleboat, these coffin canoes were without a keel,
though that involved but uncertain steering and much leeway down the dim ages.
Now when this strange circumstance was made known aft, the carpenter was at
once commanded to do Quiquake's bidding, whatever it might include. There was
some heathenish coffincoled old lumber aboard, which upon a long previous
voyage had been cut from the aboriginal groves of the Lacaday Islands, and from
these dark planks the coffin was recommended to be made. No sooner was
the carpenter apprised of the order than taking his rule he forthwith with all
the indifferent promptitude of his character proceeded into the folks and
took Quiqu's measure with great accuracy regularly chalking Quiqu's person as he
shifted the rule.
"Ah, poor fellow, he'll have to die now," ejaculated the Long Island sailor.
Going to his vice bench, the carpenter, for convenience sake and general
reference, now transferringly measured on it the exact length the coffin was to
be, and then made the transfer permanent by cutting two notches at its
extremities. This done, he marshaled the planks in his tools, and to work. When
the last nail was driven, and the lid duly planed and fitted, he lightly
shouldered the coffin, and went forward with it, inquiring whether they were
ready for it yet in that direction.
Overhearing the indignant but half-humorous cries with which the
people on deck began to drive the coffin away, Quiquake, to everyone's
consternation, commanded that the thing should be instantly brought to him. Nor
was there any denying him, seeing that of all mortals, some dying men are the
most tyrannical, and certainly, since they will shortly trouble us so little
forever more, the poor fellows ought to be indulged.
Leaning over in his hammock, Quiquake long regarded the coffin with an
attentive eye. He then called for his harpoon and had the wooden stock drawn
from it, and then had the iron part placed in the coffin along with one of
the paddles of his boat. all by his own request. Also, biscuits were then ranged
round the sides within, a flask of fresh water was placed at the head, and a
small bag of woody earth scraped up in the hold at the foot, and a piece of
sail cloth being rolled up for a pillow, Queed to be lifted into his final bed,
that he might make trial of its comforts, if any it had. He lay without
moving a few minutes, then told one to go to his bag and bring out his little
god Yojo. Then, crossing his arms on his breast with Yojo between, he called for
the coffin lid, hatch he called it, to be placed over him. The head part turned
over with a leather hinge, and there laywe in his coffin, with little but his
composed countenance in view.
"Ri, it will do. It is easy, he murmured at last, and signed to be replaced in his
hammock. But air this was done, Pip, who had been slightly hovering nearby all
this while, drew nigh to him where he lay, and with soft sobbings took him by
the hand, in the other holding his tambourine.
Poor Rover, will you never have done with all this weary roving? Where go you
now? But if the currents carry you to those sweet antillies, where the beaches
are only beat with waterlies, will you do one little errand for me? Seek out
one pip who's now been missing long. I think he's in those far antillies. If
you find him, then comfort him, for he must be very sad, for look, he's left
his tambourine behind. I found it. Riga dig dig. Now quiqu die and I'll beat your dying march.
I have heard, murmured Starbucks, gazing down the scuttle, that in violent fevers
men, all ignorance have talked in ancient tongues, and that when the
mystery is probed, it turns out always that in their wholly forgotten childhood
those ancient tongues had been really spoken in their hearing by some lofty
scholars. So to my fond faith poor pith in this strange sweetness of his lunacy
brings heavenly vouchers of all our heavenly homes. Where learned he that
but there ark he speaks again but more wildly now. Form two and two. Let's make
a general of him. Oh where's his harpoon? Lay it across here. Rigadig
dig. Huzzah. Throw for a gamecock now to sit upon his head and crow. Quiqu dies
game. Mind you that. Quiqu dies game.
Take you good heed of that. Quiqu dies game. I say game game game. But base
little pip. He died a coward. Died all a shiver. Out upon Pip. Harky. If you find
Pip tell all the Antillies he's a runaway. A coward. A coward. A coward.
Tell them he jumped from a whaleboat.
I'd never beat my tambourine over base pip and hail him general if he were once
more dying here. No, no. Shame upon all cowards. Shame upon them. Let him go
drown like Pip that jumped from a whaleboat. Shame. Shame.
During all this, Quiqu lay with closed eyes as if in a dream. Pip was led away
and the sick man was replaced in his hammock.
But now that he had apparently made every preparation for death, now that
his coffin was proved a good fit, Quiquake suddenly rallied. Soon there
seemed no need of the carpenter's box, and thereupon, when some expressed their
delighted surprise, he in substance said that the cause of his sudden
convolescence was this. At a critical moment he had just recalled a little
beauty ashore which he was leaving undone and therefore had changed his
mind about dying. He could not die yet he avered. They asked him then whether
to live or die was a matter of his own sovereign will and pleasure. He answered
certainly. In a word it was Quequake's conceit that if a man made up his mind
to live mere sickness could not kill him. nothing but a whale or a gale or
some violent ungovernable unintelligent destroyer of that sort.
Now there is this noteworthy difference between savage and civilized that while
a sick civilized man may be 6 months convolesing generally speaking a sick
savage is almost half well again in a day. So in good time my Quiquake gains
strength, and at length, after sitting on the windless for a few indolent days,
but eating with a vigorous appetite, he suddenly leaped to his feet, threw out
his arms and legs, gave himself a good stretching, yawned a little bit, and
then, springing into the head of his hoisted boat, and poisoning a harpoon,
pronounced himself fit for a fight.
With a wild whimsiness he now used his coffin for a sea chest, and emptying
into it his canvas bag of clothes, set them in order there. Many spare hours he
spent in carving the lid with all manner of grotesque figures and drawings, and
it seemed that hereby he was striving in his rude way to copy parts of the
twisted tattooing on his body. And this tattooing had been the work of a
departed prophet and seer on his island, who by those hieroglyphic marks had
written out on his body a complete theory of the heavens and the earth and
a mystical treatise on the art of attaining truth. So that Quequake in his
own proper person was a riddle to unfold, a wondrous work in one volume,
but whose mysteries not even himself could read, though his own live heart
beat against them. And these mysteries were therefore destined in the end to
moulder away with the living parchment whereon they were inscribed and so be
unsolved to the last. And this thought it must have been which suggested to
Ahab that wild exclamation of his when one morning turning away from surveying poor Quiqu.
Oh devilish tantalization of the gods.